<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE xlingpaper PUBLIC "-//XMLmind//DTD XLingPap//EN"
"XLingPap.dtd">
<xlingpaper
version="2.24.0"
><styledPaper
><lingPaper
automaticallywrapinterlinears="yes"
version="2.28.0"
><frontMatter
><title
>Suggested Steps to Follow</title
><subtitle
>when using <object
type="tAsheninka"
></object
></subtitle
><author
>H. Andrew Black</author
><affiliation
>SIL International</affiliation
><emailAddress
>asheninka_support@sil.org</emailAddress
><date
>24 September 2019</date
><version
>0.7.0 Alpha</version
><contents
></contents
></frontMatter
><section1
id="sGameToPlay"
><secTitle
>The basic “game” to play</secTitle
><p
>Setting up and using <object
type="tAsheninka"
></object
> is a bit like playing a game. One needs to make sure the crucial items are set up correctly and then one starts playing. This document outlines some suggestions on how to set up and play this game. Please see the User Documentation for more information. (Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Help / User Documentation</object
> to see it or click <link
href="UserDocumentation.pdf"
>here</link
>.)</p
><section2
id="sSetup"
><secTitle
>Setup</secTitle
><p
>The basic setup for any of the implemented approaches is as follows:</p
><ol
><li
>Create a new project (use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>File / New</object
>).<endnote
id="nSaveAs"
><p
>If you already have a project and it is very similar to what you need for this new project, you can also use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>File / Save As</object
>.</p
></endnote
></li
><li
>Make sure that what is in the <object
type="tCVSegmentInventory"
></object
> covers all the segments you have in the orthography. Depending on the orthography, you may find that you'll need to add environments for some graphemes within some segments.  For the <object
type="tONCApproach"
></object
>, check the onset, nucleus, and coda boxes as needed for each segment.</li
><li
>Make sure that every segment is in a natural class for the <object
type="tCVPatternApproach"
></object
> or is somewhere in the sonority hierarchy for the other approaches.</li
><li
>For the <object
type="tCVPatternApproach"
></object
>, create <object
type="tCVSyllablePatterns"
></object
> that cover the kinds of syllables you think the language has.  Be sure to allow for vowel-initial syllables if the language has them.</li
><li
>For the <object
type="tONCApproach"
></object
>, set the <object
type="tSyllabificationParameters"
></object
>.</li
><li
>Import a list of words (or key them one by one).</li
><li
>Back up your project (use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>File / Project Management / Back up this project</object
>).</li
></ol
><p
>With this, you have done the basic setup.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sPlayTheGame"
><secTitle
>Play the game</secTitle
><p
>You are now ready to play the game. Try the following steps:</p
><ol
><li
>Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Parser / Parse all Words</object
> to have <object
type="tAsheninka"
></object
> parse all the words in the <object
type="tCVWords"
></object
> (or <object
type="tSHWords"
></object
> or <object
type="tONCWords"
></object
>) view.</li
><li
>Look at the results. You can click on a column header to sort by that column (it currently only sorts by Unicode code point). Doing this on the <object
type="tParserResult"
></object
> column in the <object
type="tCVWords"
></object
> (or <object
type="tSHWords"
></object
> or <object
type="tONCWords"
></object
>) view will show all the words which failed at the top (at least in the English user interface language).</li
><li
>Make frequent (labeled) backups via menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>File / Project Management / Back up this project</object
>. You can make a backup, try something else (e.g., add a segment or class; re-order the syllable patterns or add a new one; adjust the sonority hierarchy; or change the <object
type="tSyllabificationParameters"
></object
>), perform the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Parser / Parse all Words</object
> process and see how it goes. If it's worse, just restore from the backup. If it's better, make a backup of that and go on.</li
></ol
><p
>This is the basic process while playing the game. In addition, the following items may be helpful, too, at various points in the process.</p
><ol
><li
>Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tools / Compare Implementations</object
> to compare a backup with what you have now or to compare two backups. This creates a report of what is different between the two states. It shows only those things which differ.</li
><li
>Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Parser / Try a Word</object
> to test various words or to try and figure out why a given word does not parse the way you expect.</li
><li
>Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tools / Find Word</object
> to look for sequences of characters, if that helps you see patterns in the data.</li
><li
>Use menu item <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tools / Predicted to correct syllabification</object
> to more quickly set which words are correctly syllabified. In fact, you should use this before exporting the results.</li
><li
>Use the <object
type="tCVPredictedVsCorrectWords"
></object
> (or <object
type="tSHPredictedVsCorrectWords"
></object
> or <object
type="tONCPredictedVsCorrectWords"
></object
>) view to discover any words whose parse does not match what is in the correct column. There may well be cases where it is not worth the effort to get the parser to correctly syllabify certain words (e.g., loan words in a different orthography or words which may well be misspelled).  In such cases, just manually set the correct syllabification and do not worry that these fail to parse successfully.</li
></ol
></section2
></section1
><backMatter
><endnotes
></endnotes
><references
></references
></backMatter
><xi:include
href="Languages.xml"
xpointer="element(/1)"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
></xi:include
><xi:include
href="Types.xml"
xpointer="element(/1)"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
></xi:include
><xi:include
href="IndexTerms.xml"
xpointer="element(/1)"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
></xi:include
></lingPaper
><xi:include
href="SILInternationalPaperStylesheet.xml"
xpointer="element(/1)"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
></xi:include
></styledPaper
></xlingpaper
>
